<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>TidyTuesday on </title>
    <link>/categories/tidytuesday/</link>
    <description>Recent content in TidyTuesday on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/tidytuesday/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>TidyTuesday: Wine Ratings</title>
      <link>/post/tidytuesday-wine-ratings/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/tidytuesday-wine-ratings/</guid>
      <description>I finished my first year of grad school two weeks ago and I’ve been enjoying the break before my summer work starts next Monday. As part of this time off, I’ve been able to devote a good bit of time to the Tidy Tuesday datasets and learning new figures and visualization tools - my extracurriculars. This week’s dataset was about 130k wine tasting ratings.
There was a lot of potential in this dataset, which includes information for each wine regarding its name and variety, country, county/province, and other region of production, price per bottle, rating (on a scale from 0-100, but only wines with ratings above 80 are given), the name and Twitter handle of the wine taster, and notes from the taster based on their thoughts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TidyTuesday: Global Plastic Waste Management</title>
      <link>/post/tidytuesday-global-plastic-waste-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/tidytuesday-global-plastic-waste-management/</guid>
      <description>A few weeks ago I began participating in R’s community TidyTuesday; a community-based data visualization challenge, where a new dataset is released on Tuesday and participants are invited to create visualizations in the tidyverse. I’ve only participated a few times, but have learned so much already from seeing others’ figures and analysis routes, following along with code, and getting feedback. Twitter proves once again to be an excellent learning tool.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>