<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data-naut</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Data-naut</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>TidyTuesday: Global Plastic Waste Management</title>
      <link>/post/tidytuesday-global-plastic-waste-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/tidytuesday-global-plastic-waste-management/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago I began participating in R’s community &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rfordatascience/tidytuesday&#34;&gt;TidyTuesday&lt;/a&gt;; a community-based data visualization challenge, where a new dataset is released on Tuesday and participants are invited to create visualizations in the tidyverse. I’ve only participated a few times, but have learned so much already from seeing others’ figures and analysis routes, following along with code, and getting feedback. Twitter proves once again to be an excellent learning tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This past week’s dataset looked at global plastic waste (mis)management. Below I provide some of the code and figures I produced in exploring this data. As always, I wish the dataset provided us with even more information to wade through. Although, part of the fun is coming up with meaningful analysis from seemingly few variables. My code is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/alyssamv/tidytuesdays/blob/master/2019/GlobalWaste_0521/GlobalWaste.Rmd&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this dataset we find data about global plastic waste disposal in 2010. We also get information about county 2011 GDP, and coastal and total population according to Gapminder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In looking at the distributions in the data, I noticed that there were around 50 missing values for several of the variables related to plastic waste. I explored a little bit the population and GDP attributes of these countries compared to others, and found that most of these countries with missing information fall in the 50th percentile for GDP. Let’s take a look at some of the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2019-05-27-tidytuesday-global-plastic-waste-management_files/figure-html/scatter-1.png&#34; width=&#34;768&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This figure also gives us some information about the distribution of population and GDP across the world. There are some outliers in both, with significantly large population and GDP, not shown in the scatter plot (China, India, and the USA).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next I started to look at the data on waste, and specifically the relationship between waste management and GDP/population. “Mismanaged waste” is defined by &lt;a href=&#34;https://ourworldindata.org/plastic-pollution&#34;&gt;Our World in Data&lt;/a&gt;, the data source, as “material which is either littered or inadequately disposed”. First I plotted some scatterplots to get a feel for the association (if any). Below, we can see that the trend if such that richer countries have less waste per capita.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2019-05-27-tidytuesday-global-plastic-waste-management_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I want to present the above information as a map, highlighting the top three countries (with regard to population and GDP) USA, China, and India.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2019-05-27-tidytuesday-global-plastic-waste-management_files/figure-html/map-1.png&#34; width=&#34;1248&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, within each country, what percentage of their total plastic waste is being mismanaged? Does this also correspond to a country’s wealth? I decided to look at a scatterplot with overlaid boxplots across continents and levels of wealth (percentiles of GDP). It looks like the higher a country’s GDP per capita, the less of its plastic is being mismanaged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2019-05-27-tidytuesday-global-plastic-waste-management_files/figure-html/boxplots-1.png&#34; width=&#34;960&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Survey of early phase trial designs in oncology</title>
      <link>/post/survey-of-early-phase-trial-designs-in-oncology/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/survey-of-early-phase-trial-designs-in-oncology/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;After a few years of working with clinical trial methodology, I finally decided to put together a introductory guide to common trial designs seen in oncology drug development. The goal here is to provide (1) a brief summary of each phase and the common designs used, (2) some of the most popular areas of interest (eg randomization) and new methods that aim to address them, and (3) a summary of the biggest issues that clinicians/statisticians face in testing new agents. I will also be providing papers that I’ve found really useful/important in my own learning about this topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few notes on the material in this post: as a statistician in training, I will be talking about the statistical nature of the designs presented. I may present formulas, but will try to define as many terms as possible in order to appeal to a range of disciplines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that, let’s dive in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;oncology-research&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Oncology research&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me first give a brief overview of research in oncology, because the landscape in this disease setting is different than in infectious diseases or psychiatry, for example. It’s a complex field. There are dozens of tumor types; location in the body, solid vs. other tumors, mutations, biomarker subtypes, etc. All of these factors make for tumors that respond very differently to different therapies. Consider HER-2 positive breast cancer, which is more difficult to treat than the HER-2 negative variant due to the aggression of the growth of tumor cells.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With research in any disease, we care about clinical outcomes. That is, improving the lives of patients. In cancer, this is most easily measured as survival time. So, when the goal or endpoint of a trial is specified, it often relates to these survival outcomes. But things like toxicity and quality of life are also important measures of how well a treatment is working. More on this topic later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;drug-development&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Drug development&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re unfamiliar with the drug development process as regulated by the US Food &amp;amp; Drug Administration (FDA), I will give an overview here. Feel free to skip down to details of trial designs below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, there are five stages of development: (1) discovery and development of the molecule, (2) preclinical research, ie not in humans, (3) clinical research in humans, (4) FDA review, and (5) FDA post-market monitoring. I focus in this post on stage 3, clinical trials, which is broken down into three testing phases. &lt;strong&gt;Phase I&lt;/strong&gt; is generally intended to test the safety of the new agent, and is tested only in a small number (dozens) of subjects. Once safety is established, &lt;strong&gt;phase II&lt;/strong&gt; begins to test the efficacy while continuing to monitor safety, in more patients than phase I (dozens to a couple hundred). If it is determined that the experimental drug shows promising efficacy, it moves to phase III. &lt;strong&gt;Phase III&lt;/strong&gt; seeks to establish how the efficacy of the new drug compares to that of some other existing treatment, usually the best available therapy. And this is often done in hundreds or thousands of subjects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, how is a new agent deemed to be safe or efficacious enough to move forward to the next phase? Excellent question. The answer is not so simple, and this is where statistics come into play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, frequentist hypothesis testing came to save us all. Now we can test whether a drug is safe or effective and claim statistical significance when the p-value falls below that megical number 0.05 (or whatever we specify to be).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some important definitions before we continue: &lt;strong&gt;Endpoint&lt;/strong&gt;: quantity we are measuring / testing in the trial; &lt;strong&gt;Surrogate endpoint&lt;/strong&gt;: this actually has a very specific definition, but is essentially a proxy for the endpoint we really want to measure. The surrogate is used because it is easier to measure. It must be shown to do an adequate job of predicting the real outcome of interest;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;phase-i&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Phase I&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Historically, phase I studies were intended to test the safety of new drug, where we want to find the dose we would want to carry forward to phase II. This dose (the classic endpoint of this phase) is the Maximum Tolerated Dose, or MTD, which is defined as the highest dose with acceptable toxicity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;phase-ii&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Phase II&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;phase-iii&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Phase III&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Slides</title>
      <link>/slides/example/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/slides/example/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;welcome-to-slides&#34;&gt;Welcome to Slides&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Academic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;features&#34;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Efficiently write slides in Markdown&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3-in-1: Create, Present, and Publish your slides&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Supports speaker notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mobile friendly slides&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;controls&#34;&gt;Controls&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next: &lt;code&gt;Right Arrow&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;Space&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Previous: &lt;code&gt;Left Arrow&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start: &lt;code&gt;Home&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finish: &lt;code&gt;End&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overview: &lt;code&gt;Esc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speaker notes: &lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fullscreen: &lt;code&gt;F&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zoom: &lt;code&gt;Alt + Click&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/hakimel/reveal.js#pdf-export&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PDF Export&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;code&gt;E&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;code-highlighting&#34;&gt;Code Highlighting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inline code: &lt;code&gt;variable&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Code block:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34;&gt;porridge = &amp;quot;blueberry&amp;quot;
if porridge == &amp;quot;blueberry&amp;quot;:
    print(&amp;quot;Eating...&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;math&#34;&gt;Math&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In-line math: $x + y = z$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Block math:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$$
f\left( x \right) = \;\frac{{2\left( {x + 4} \right)\left( {x - 4} \right)}}{{\left( {x + 4} \right)\left( {x + 1} \right)}}
$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fragments&#34;&gt;Fragments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make content appear incrementally&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;{{% fragment %}} One {{% /fragment %}}
{{% fragment %}} **Two** {{% /fragment %}}
{{% fragment %}} Three {{% /fragment %}}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press &lt;code&gt;Space&lt;/code&gt; to play!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;fragment &#34; &gt;
   One
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;fragment &#34; &gt;
   &lt;strong&gt;Two&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;fragment &#34; &gt;
   Three
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fragment can accept two optional parameters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;class&lt;/code&gt;: use a custom style (requires definition in custom CSS)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;weight&lt;/code&gt;: sets the order in which a fragment appears&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;speaker-notes&#34;&gt;Speaker Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add speaker notes to your presentation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-markdown&#34;&gt;{{% speaker_note %}}
- Only the speaker can read these notes
- Press `S` key to view
{{% /speaker_note %}}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press the &lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt; key to view the speaker notes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside class=&#34;notes&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only the speaker can read these notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Press &lt;code&gt;S&lt;/code&gt; key to view&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;themes&#34;&gt;Themes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;black: Black background, white text, blue links (default)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;white: White background, black text, blue links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;league: Gray background, white text, blue links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;beige: Beige background, dark text, brown links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sky: Blue background, thin dark text, blue links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;night: Black background, thick white text, orange links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;serif: Cappuccino background, gray text, brown links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;simple: White background, black text, blue links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;solarized: Cream-colored background, dark green text, blue links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;


&lt;section data-noprocess data-shortcode-slide
  
      
      data-background-image=&#34;/img/boards.jpg&#34;
  &gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;custom-slide&#34;&gt;Custom Slide&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Customize the slide style and background&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-markdown&#34;&gt;{{&amp;lt; slide background-image=&amp;quot;/img/boards.jpg&amp;quot; &amp;gt;}}
{{&amp;lt; slide background-color=&amp;quot;#0000FF&amp;quot; &amp;gt;}}
{{&amp;lt; slide class=&amp;quot;my-style&amp;quot; &amp;gt;}}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;custom-css-example&#34;&gt;Custom CSS Example&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s make headers navy colored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Create &lt;code&gt;assets/css/reveal_custom.css&lt;/code&gt; with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-css&#34;&gt;.reveal section h1,
.reveal section h2,
.reveal section h3 {
  color: navy;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;questions&#34;&gt;Questions?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://discourse.gohugo.io&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Ask&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Oncology Drug Development Resources</title>
      <link>/project/drug-dev-resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/drug-dev-resources/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>iAdapt</title>
      <link>/project/internal-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/internal-project/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Privacy Policy</title>
      <link>/privacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/privacy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The clinical trials landscape for glioblastoma: is it adequate to develop new treatments?</title>
      <link>/publication/gbm_meta-analysis1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/gbm_meta-analysis1/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Divining responder populations from survival data</title>
      <link>/publication/diving-responder-pops/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/diving-responder-pops/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
